McCulloch mss., 1766-1914 LMC 1694
Lilly Library
McCulloch mss.
1766-1914
1944
1948
1950
1951
Lilly Library
LMC 1694
1 folio oversize
1 bound
10 Boxes 10 standard
The McCulloch mss., 1766-1914, consist of letters and papers of Hugh McCulloch, 1808-1895, U.S. Comptroller of the Currency, Secretary of the Treasury, and a partner in the London banking house of Jay Cooke, McCulloch & Company.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
Hugh McCulloch was born December 7, 1808, in Kennebunk, Maine, the son of Hugh and Abigail (Perkins) McCulloch. He attended Bowdoin College from 1825-1827, after which he taught school then went to study law in Boston. He was admitted to the bar in 1833 and migrated to Fort Wayne, Indiana, where he began practicing law. In 1834, he married Eunice Hardy. After her early death in 1836, he remarried to Susan Maria Man on March 21, 1838. McCulloch was cashier and manager of the Fort Wayne branch of the State Bank of Indiana, and served as director from 1835 to 1856, after which he was president of the Bank of Indiana from 1856 to 1863. In 1863, he was selected to be U.S. Comptroller of the Currency, a position he held until he was appointed by president Abraham Lincoln as Secretary of the Treasury, serving 1865-1869. On November 9, 1870, McCulloch sailed for Liverpool to inaugurate the London banking firm of Jay Cooke, McCulloch & Co., which was established in March 1871 and survived the failure of the affiliated American house of Jay Cooke & Co. in 1873. The banking firm was reorganized around 1875 as McCulloch & Co., from which he retired on June 30, 1879. From 1880-1885, he was president of the International Chemical Company of New York. During that period, he again served as Secretary of the Treasury from October, 1884-March, 1885. In 1888, he published Men and Measures of Half a Century. He died on May 24, 1895, at his home, Holly Hill, in Prince George's County, Maryland.
Scope and Content Note
The manuscripts in this collection consist of family, business, and official correspondence and papers. Included are unbound letters and papers, 1766-1914, and bound materials consisting 30 letter copybooks, 1864-1869 and 1879-1893; 5 scrapbooks; and a household account book of Marie Louise McCulloch, (Mrs. John Brooks Yale), daughter of Hugh McCulloch, Nov. 9, 1878- May 1, 1879 and Oct. 25, 1881-June 11, 1883. The first folder in the collection contains biographical and genealogical material about the family. Completing the collection is an oversize folder containing a document certifying Hugh McCulloch's election to Probate Judge of Allen County, Indiana, November 7, 1834.
The unbound materials consist in the main of business correspondence of Hugh McCulloch relating to the firm of Jay Cooke, McCulloch & Co. and its successor, McCulloch & Co., the International Chemical Company of New York, and other business interests; and of family correspondence and letters from friends. Included is a considerable amount of personal correspondence of Mrs. Susan Maria (Man) McCulloch, (Mrs. Hugh McCulloch). The unbound materials fall principally in the 1870s and 1880s. For 1866-1869 some of McCulloch's Treasury correspondence is included. Letters from 1895-1898 are correspondence of Mrs. Hugh McCulloch, and from 1898-1914 of Mrs. John Brooks Yale.
The letter copybooks are in three series: letter copybooks, Aug. 18, 1864-Mar. 3, 1869, of John Aikman Stewart and Henry Herbert Van Dyck, Assistant Treasurers of the U.S., New York, New York, 10 volumes; letter copybooks, Mar. 9, 1865-Mar. 3, 1869, of Hugh McCulloch as Secretary of the Treasury, 17 volumes; personal business letter copybooks of Hugh McCulloch, June 3, 1879-Jan. 17, 1881, and Aug. 27, 1881-May 2, 1893, 3 volumes.
Correspondents represented in this collection include Cuyler Adams, Alvey Augustus Adee, Alexander Agassiz, William Boyd Allison, Henry Bowen Anthony, Susan Brownell Anthony, Chester Alan Arthur, George Fisher Baker, Frederick Augustus Porter Bernard, William Milo Barnum, Samuel Colcord Bartlett, Thomas Francis Bayard, Charles Beecher, Henry Ward Beecher, Robert Lenox Belknap, Joel Benton, Frederick Billings, George Bliss, Albert Sidney Bolles, George Sewall Boutwell, Samuel Bowles, David Josiah Brewer, Sir Frederick William Adolphus Bruce, John Burroughs, Benjamin Butterworth, George Washington Cable, Henry White Cannon, Thomas Lincoln Casey, Daniel Henry Chamberlain, George William Childs, Grover Cleveland, Rose Elizabeth Cleveland, William Wilkie Collins, Henry David Cooke, Jay Cooke, Samuel Sullivan Cox, Frank Crisp, Charles Crocker, Uriel Haskell Crocker, George Ticknor Curtis, George William Curtis, Anson Dart, Charles Devens, William Earl Dodge, William P. Dole, Lyman Copeland Draper, Charles Franklin Dunbar, William McKee Dunn, Alfred Peck Edgerton, Charles William Eliot, Frank H. Evans, William Maxwell Evarts, Harris Charles Fahnestock, Charles Stebbins Fairchild, Thomas Fickus, Mary Katherine Keemle Field, Stephen Johnson Field, Joseph Benson Foraker, John Murray Forbes, Worthington Chauncey Ford, Francis Ormond French, William Pierce Frye, John Work Garrett, Randall Lee Gibson, Arthur Pue Gorman, Frank Wakeley Gunsaulus, Charles Henry Hall, Andrew Holman Hamilton, Henry B. Hammond, Benjamin Harrison, Mrs. Caroline Lavinia (Scott) Harrison, Mrs. Mary Scott (Lord) Harrison, Joel Tanner Hart, Mrs. Mary Anne (Man) Hawkins, Rutherford Birchard Hayes, Hinton Rowan Helper, Joseph Henry, Hilary Abner Herbert, Abram Stevens Hewitt, John Hampden Holliday, Samuel Dana Horton, Mrs. Julia (Ward) Howe, Henry Hulbert Ingersoll, Robert Green Ingersoll, William Mills Ivins, Hugh Judge Jewett, Andrew Johnson, Edward B. Judson, George Washington Julian, Henry Purkitt Kidden, Gazaway Bugg Lamar, James Franklin Doughty Lanier, James Laurence Laughlin, William Andrew Leonard, Robert Todd Lincoln, Jenny Marcia Lind-Goldshmidt, Seth Low, Charles A. O. McClellan, John McClure, Charles McCulloch, Mrs. Susan Maria (Man) McCulloch, Daniel Manning, LaSalle Almeron Maynard, Montgomery Cunningham Meigs, R. L. Melville, Catharine Merrill, William Henry Harrison Miller, Robert Grier Monroe, Frank Moore, Benjamin Moran, Justin Smith Morrill, Samuel E. Morss, Henry Loomis Nelson, Simon Newcomb, William Ellis Niblack, William Paret, Henry C. Parsons, Benjamin Pierce, Ebenezer Jenckes Penniman, Solomon Newton Pettis, Edwards Pierrepont, Horace Porter, Thomas Bayley Potter, Redfield Proctor, Sir John Henry Puleston, Lewis Van Syckle Fitz Randolph, Rastus Seneca Ransom, Whitelaw Reid, Allen Thorndike Rice, William Adams Richardson, Edward Hastings Ripley, Jacob W. Schuckers, Thomas Alexander Scott, William Henry Seward, Philip Henry Sheridan, John Sherman, William Tecumseh Sherman, James Luther Slayden, George Washburn Smalley, F. L. Soames, Richard Spencer, Francis Elias Spinner, Simon Sterne, Thaddeus Stevens, John Aikman Stewart, William Strong, James Moore Swank, Svante Magnus Swenson, Henry Moore Teller, Eli Thayer, George Clifford Thomas, John Edgar Thomson, Queen Victoria, Henry Villard, Daniel Wolsey Voorhees, Henry Randall Waite, William Hayes Ward, Brainard Henry Warner, John DeWitt Warner, Lewis W. Washington, Daniel Webster, David Ames Wells, William Collins Whitney, James Grant Wilson, William Windom, George Wood Wingate, Stewart Lyndon Woodford, Maxwell Van Zandt Woodhull, Charles Barstow Wright.
Note on Indexing Term - "United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865": There is some material from the Civil War era.
Note on Indexing Term - "Women": Includes personal correspondence, household account books, and scrapbooks of his wife Susan Maria (Man) McCulloch (1818-98) and of their daughter Marie Louise. Dating from the 1870s and 1880s, the women's letters pertain to family and social matters.
Acquisition Information
Purchase: 1944, 1948, 1950, 1951
Indiana--Politics and government; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865; Women; McCulloch, Hugh, 1808-1895; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865
- 1766-1872 (Box 1)
- 1873-1878, Aug. (Box 2)
- 1878, Sept.-1885, Aug. (Box 3)
- 1885, Sept.-1894 (Box 4)
- ; undated, 1895-1914 (Box 5)
- Letter copybooks of John Aikman Stewart and Henry Herbert Van Dyck, Assistant Treasurers of the U.S., New York, New York., Aug. 18, 1864-Mar. 3, 1869 (Bound [1])
  Scope and Contents
  10 volumes
- Letter copybooks of Hugh McCulloch as Secretary of the Treasury., Mar. 9, 1865-Mar. 3, 1869 (Bound [2])
  17 volumes
- Personal business letter copybooks of Hugh McCulloch. and, June 3, 1879-Jan. 17, 1881; Aug. 27, 1881-May 2, 1893 (Bound [3])
  3 volumes
- Scrapbooks (Bound [4])
  5 volumes
- McCulloch, Marie. Household Accounts. and, Nov. 9, 1878-May 1, 1879; Oct. 25, 1881-June 11, 1883 (Bound [5])
- McCulloch, Hugh. Election to Probate Judge of Allen County, Indiana., November 7, 1834 (Ovflat 14)